Inventory of the Mrs. J. E. Thane (Laura Thane Whipple) papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Mrs. J. E. Thane (Laura Thane Whipple) papers
1897-1936
58026
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box 0.4 linear feet
Correspondence, printed matter, and miscellanea, relating to food conservation in Alameda County and to European relief work of various organizations during World War I.
Thane, Mrs. J. E.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1958.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
Laura Thane Whipple was born in 1875 and died in 1966. She was the United States Food Administration Woman Director of Food Conservation for Alameda County, California, during World War I.
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers contain correspondence, printed matter, and miscellanea, relating to food conservation in Alameda County and to European relief work of various organizations during World War I. The papers include official guidelines for conservation of food and household items, with an emphasis on relief in Belgium and France. Two main organizations reflected in the papers include the United States Food Administration and Department of Agriculture.
United States. Food Administration.; Alameda County (Calif.); International relief.; World War, 1914-1918--Civilian relief.; World War, 1914-1918--Food question.; World War, 1914-1918--United States.
- Correspondence, 1917-1936 (Box-folder 1: 1-2)
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains letters from the Friends of Belgium organization, Alameda County Republican Assembly, and the Republican State Committee.
- Miscellaneous correspondence and U.S. Food Administration reports and guidelines, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  Contains reports and direct correspondence from the United States Food Administration in Washington, D.C. Includes home conservation guidelines for women in charge of purchasing and preparing food for their family.
- Photographs, 1906, undated (Box-folder 1: 4)
  One print of an unidentified woman and one print of an unidentified man and woman in a Red Cross car.
- Postcards of Henriette, Queen of Belgium, undated (Box-folder 1: 5)
- Pamphlet on La Loie Fuller, undated (Box-folder 1: 6)
  Relates to Red Cross of Romania.
- Food and relief, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  Emphasis on shipment records and logistics for Belgium and France.
- Sugar permits, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  Includes Red Cross signs, memoranda from the U.S. Treasury Department regarding conservation and the war effort, and U.S. Department of Agriculture Weekly Newsletter.
- Newspapers and clippings, 1911-1924, undated (Box-folder 1: 9)
  Includes The Call, San Francisco; The Township Register, Alameda County; Oakland Edition of the San Francisco Examiner.
- Printed materials, 1897, undated (Box-folder 1: 10)
  Includes The Spirt of the Nation, a pamphlet containing influential American songs and documents. Other items include war time aid booklets, encouraging Americans to do their part.
- U.S. Department of Agriculture, U.S. Food Administration, and U.S. Treasury printed materials, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 11)
- U.S. Department of Agriculture and U.S. Food Administration official printed reports and news releases, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 1: 12)
- U.S. Food Administration, Official Food Bulletin, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 13)
- U.S. Food Administration reports, Alameda County, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 14)
- Miscellaneous, 1919, undated (Box-folder 1: 15)
  Includes U.S. Food Administration promotional signs and sugar purchase receipts.
- Herbert Hoover campaign door sign, circa 1928 (Box-folder 1: 16)